<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="jbpm31">
  <title>jBPM 3.1.x</title>

  <important>
    <para>The following documentation can be used as reference documentation
    for Spring Modules jBPM 3.0.x support as well.</para>
  </important>

  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>jBPM module offers integration between the <ulink
    url="http://www.springframework.org/">Spring</ulink> and <ulink
    url="http://www.jboss.com/products/jbpm/">jBPM</ulink> allowing for reuse
    of Spring's <ulink url="http://www.hibernate.org">Hibernate</ulink>
    support along with the IoC container. The module allows jBPM's underlying
    Hibernate sessionFactory to be configured through Spring and jBPM actions
    to access Spring's context.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Configuration</title>

    <para>Users familiar with Spring will see that the jBPM module structure
    resembles with the orm package from the main Spring distribution. The
    module offers a central template class for working with jBPM, a callback
    to access the native JbpmContext and a local factory bean for
    configuration and creating a jBPM instance.</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;beans&gt;
  &lt;!-- DataSource definition --&gt;
  &lt;bean id="dataSource" class="..."&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/bean&gt;

  &lt;!-- Hibernate SessionFactory definition --&gt;
  &lt;bean id="hibernateSessionFactory" class="org.springframework.orm.hibernate3.LocalSessionFactoryBean"&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/bean&gt;

  &lt;!-- helper for reading jBPM process definitions --&gt;
  &lt;bean id="simpleWorkflow" class="org.springmodules.workflow.jbpm31.definition.ProcessDefinitionFactoryBean"&gt;
    &lt;property name="definitionLocation" value="classpath:org/springmodules/workflow/jbpm31/simpleWorkflow.xml"/&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;

  &lt;!-- jBPM configuration --&gt;
  &lt;bean id="jbpmConfiguration" class="org.springmodules.workflow.jbpm31.LocalJbpmConfigurationFactoryBean"&gt;
    &lt;property name="sessionFactory" ref="hibernateSessionFactory"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="configuration" value="classpath:jbpm.cfg.xml"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="processDefinitions"&gt;
     &lt;list&gt;
      &lt;ref local="simpleWorkflow"/&gt;
     &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property name="createSchema" value="true"/&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;

 &lt;!-- jBPM template --&gt;
 &lt;bean id="jbpmTemplate" class="org.springmodules.workflow.jbpm31.JbpmTemplate"&gt;
  &lt;constructor-arg index="0" ref="jbpmConfiguration"/&gt;
  &lt;constructor-arg index="1" ref="simpleWorkflow"/&gt;
 &lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;/beans&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>The example above shows how (existing) Spring-managed Hibernate
    SessionFactories and transaction management can be reused with
    jBPM.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>LocalJbpmConfigurationFactoryBean</title>

      <para>The main element is
      <emphasis>LocalJbpmConfigurationFactoryBean</emphasis> which should be
      familiar to users acustomed to Spring. Based on the jbpm configuration
      file and the given SessionFactory, it will create a jBPM configuration
      which can be used for working with the given process definitions. It is
      possible to replace jBPM xml configuration with jBPM 3.1.x newly added
      ObjectFactory - note that if both are present the xml configuration is
      preffered. <emphasis>LocalJbpmConfigurationFactoryBean</emphasis> allows
      the creation of the underlying schema based on the process definitions
      loaded automatically at startup.</para>

      <para>Note that the sessionFactory property is not mandatory - Hibernate
      SessionFactory can be reused with jBPM or jBPM can work by itself
      without any integration with the existing infrastructure. However, in
      most scenarios, using
      <emphasis>LocalJbpmConfigurationFactoryBean</emphasis> allows one to
      take advantage of Spring <ulink
      url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/2.0.x/reference/transaction.html">transaction
      management infrastructure</ulink> so it's possible without any code
      change to use jBPM, Hibernate and jdbc-based code inside the same
      transactional context, be it managed locally or globally (JTA).
      Moreover, it is possible to use <ulink
      url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/2.0.x/reference/orm.html#orm-hibernate">thread-bound</ulink>
      session or OpenSessionInView patterns with jBPM.</para>

      <para><emphasis>LocalJbpmConfigurationFactoryBean</emphasis> is also
      aware of the enclosing applicationContext lifecycle - jBPM will be
      initialized once the context is started (usually application startup)
      and will be closed properly when the context is destroyed (application
      is shutdown).</para>

      <para>Note that <emphasis>LocalJbpmConfigurationFactoryBean</emphasis>
      can be configured programatically and can be used standalone only to
      build an jBPM context which can be used independently of Spring Modules
      jBPM support.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Inversion of Control: JbpmTemplate and JbpmCallback</title>

      <para>Another important feature of Spring Modules jBPM support is
      <emphasis>JbpmTemplate</emphasis>. The template offers very convient
      ways of working directly with process definitions as well as jBPM API
      taking care of handling exceptions (be it jBPM or Hibernate based) in
      respect to the ongoing transaction (if it's present), the underlying
      Hibernate session (if pesistent services are used) and the jBPM context.
      jBPM exceptions (and the underlying Hibernate information) are
      translated into Spring's DAO exception hierarchy. Everything happens in
      a transparent and consistent manner.This is possible, as with every
      Spring-style template,even when direct access to the native JbpmContext
      is desired, through the <emphasis>JbpmCallback</emphasis>:</para>

      <para><programlisting>public ProcessInstance findProcessInstance(final Long processInstanceId) {
  return (ProcessInstance) execute(new JbpmCallback() {
   public Object doInJbpm(JbpmContext context) {
    // do something
    ...
    return context.getGraphSession().loadProcessInstance(processInstanceId.longValue());
   }
  });
}</programlisting>As well, as
      <emphasis>LocalJbpmConfigurationFactoryBean</emphasis>, the
      <emphasis>JbpmTemplate</emphasis> can be configured programatically and
      can be used standalone on a pre-existing jbpmContext (configured through
      <emphasis>LocalJbpmConfigurationFactoryBean</emphasis> or not) and can
      be used independently of Spring Modules jBPM support.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>ProcessDefinitionFactoryBean</title>

      <para><emphasis>ProcessDefinitionFactoryBean</emphasis> is a simple
      reader that loads jBPM process definition using Spring's <ulink
      url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/2.0.x/reference/resources.html#d0e4913">ResourceLoader</ulink>s.
      Thus, the xml files can be load using the classpath, relative or
      absolute file path or even from the Servlet Context. See the official
      <ulink
      url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/2.0.x/reference/resources.html">documentation</ulink>
      for more information.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Outside Spring container</title>

      <para>It is important to note that while our example showed
      LocalJbpmConfigurationFactoryBean and JbpmTemplate template inside a
      Spring xml, these classes do not depend on each other or on Spring
      application context. They can be just as well configured programatically
      and can</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Accessing Spring beans from jBPM actions</title>

    <para>Another important feature of Spring Modules jBPM integration is
    allowing Spring configured beans to be reused inside jBPM actions. This
    allows one to leverage Spring container capabilities (bean lifecycles,
    scoping, injection, proxying just to name a few) in a transparent way with
    jBPM. Consider the following Spring application context:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;beans&gt;
 &lt;!-- Spring bean visible inside jBPM processed --&gt;
 &lt;bean id="jbpmAction" class="org.MyJbpmActionHandler" singleton="true"&gt;
   &lt;property name="someProp" ref="anotherBean"/&gt;
   ...
 &lt;/bean&gt;
..
&lt;/beans&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>and jBPM process definition:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;

&lt;process-definition name="simpleWorkflow"&gt;
 &lt;start-state&gt;
  &lt;transition to="myState"&gt;
  &lt;/transition&gt;
 &lt;/start-state&gt;

 &lt;state name="myState"&gt;
  &lt;transition to="end"&gt;
   &lt;action name="myAction" config-type="bean" class="org.springmodules.workflow.jbpm31.JbpmHandlerProxy"&gt;
    &lt;targetBean&gt;jbpmAction&lt;/targetBean&gt;
    &lt;factoryKey&gt;jbpmConfiguration&lt;/factoryKey&gt;
   &lt;/action&gt;
  &lt;/transition&gt;
 &lt;/state&gt;

 &lt;end-state name="end"/&gt;
&lt;/process-definition&gt;</programlisting>

    <para><emphasis>JbpmHandlerProxy</emphasis> transparently locates Spring
    applicationContext and searches the bean identified by the
    <emphasis>targetBean</emphasis> parameter (in this case jbpmAction) and
    delegate all calls to the jBPM action. This way, one is not limited only
    to the injection offered by jBPM container and can integrate and
    communicate in a very easy manner with other Spring managed beans.
    Moreover, your action lifecycle can be sigleton (one shared instance) or
    prototype (every call gets a new instance) or in Spring 2.0 scoped to a
    certain application component (like one instance per http session).</para>

    <para>The optional <emphasis>factoryKey</emphasis> parameter specified in
    this example should be used when one is dealing with more then one jBPM
    configuration inside the same classloader (not common in practice). The
    <emphasis>factoryKey</emphasis> should be the same as the bean name of the
    <emphasis>LocalJbpmConfigurationFactoryBean</emphasis> to be used (in our
    case jbpmConfiguration).</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>